This was a real invention, and it was
unveiled to the public in 1910 by its
inventor, Louis Brennan. The idea was
that using a single rail instead of two
would make trains faster and railways
cheaper to build. His train could take
corners at greater speeds without being
thrown off the tracks. In order to
understand exactly what's going on here,
we need to know a bit about gyroscopes.
The basic principle is that if you spin
a disc really quickly, its angular
momentum tries to keep it perfectly
stable. If you try to tilt it in this
direction, it starts rotating on the
vertical axis. This is called
precession. But, if instead of tilting
it, we cause it to precess, it actually
tilts the disc in the opposite
direction. It's because of this that a
gyro will always try to find its way
back to equilibrium. Brennan saw this as
the key to keeping his train balanced.
He experimented by placing a small
flywheel in a model train and hooking it
up to an electric motor. Initially, this
worked, and anytime the train started to
fall, the disc would precess and keep
the train upright. The problem was that
when the train turned, the gyro didn't
turn with it, since it was trying to
maintain its position in space. From the
train's point of view, the gyro was
precessing, which caused the train to
tilt over and fall off the track. To
solve this problem, Brennan put a second
gyro in the train and made it spin in
the opposite direction. Both were
connected by a gear, so that when one
gyro precessed, the other would precess
in the exact opposite direction. When
the train turned a corner, both gyros
wanted to keep facing the same way, but
this was impossible. And so, both gyros
were forced to rotate with the train,
and this unwanted precession got
canceled out. With another problem
solved, he started working on the
full-size prototype that he could test
with real passengers.